[wind gusting]
[mysterious music playing]
[music intensifies]
[ethereal vocalizing]
[narrator] Many years later
as he faced the firing squad.
Colonel Aureliano Buendía
was to remember that distant afternoon
when his father took him to discover ice.
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
-[lively music playing]
-[men shouting. whooping]
[whooping continues]
[narrator] José Arcadio Buendía
and Úrsula Iguarán were cousins.
They had been raised together
in the old village
that their ancestors had transformed into
one of the finest towns in the province.
-[lively music continues]
-[men] Hey! [laughing]
José Arcadio Buendía. let Úrsula breathe.
Just hold on a little longer. man!
Come on!
Let's celebrate! This party's yours!
-Come on. let's go. Come on!
-Come on. come on. come on. come on.
[lively music continues]
[all cheering. whooping]
[narrator] Although their marriage
was to be expected.
when they expressed
their desire to be wed.
their relatives tried to stop it.
[all laughing. whooping]
[man laughing]
They feared that after centuries
of their two races being
secularly crossed.
their two healthy products would suffer
the shame of breeding iguanas.
[whooping. shouting]
[ethereal music playing]
[lively music fades]
[narrator] They would have been happy
had Úrsula's mother not terrorized her
with all sorts of sinister predictions
about their offspring.
[lively live music resumes]
[all] Hey! Hey! Hey!
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!
-[lively music continues]
-[ethereal music continues]
Hey. hey. Get over here.
[all cheering]
[man chanting]
[lively music intensifies]
[man continues chanting]
-[music ends]
-[man] Hey!
[door creaks]
[panting]
[Úrsula moaning softly]
[both panting]
What's this?
Mother gave it to me.
I can't believe she's still tormenting you
with all of her superstitions
or that you even listen to her.
No. they're not superstitions.
This time what she said was awful.
What's more awful than making
you wear all those belts?
Raising a monster.
Two of my mother's cousins
got married and they had a son.
The child had a shameful deformity
he suffered with his whole life.
A deformity of what sort?
He had a pig's tail.
shaped like a corkscrew
with a small tuft of hair on the tip.
[snickering]
Why would she lie about that?
She said the poor man bled out
after a butcher friend of his
cut the tail off with a cleaver.
I'm fine having piglets with you.
I don't care.
as long as they're able to talk.
I am not fine with it.
I'm not going to have pigs for children.
[exhales]
[sighs]
[mysterious music playing]
[narrator] During the day.
he would take care of
his fighting roosters
and she would embroider.
[tense music playing]
[narrator] At night.
they would wrestle for several hours
in a state of anguished violence
that seemed to be a substitute
for the act of making love.
[mysterious music resumes]
[goats bleating]
[tense music resumes]
[breathing heavily]
José Arcadio Buendía and Úrsula Iguarán
lived this way for several months.
[music fades]
[goats bleating]
[rooster crowing]
[man] I thought
you'd never come. my friend.
I bet a lot of money on your rooster.
He's ready. right?
If he's here.
it's because he's ready. my friend.
[chuckles]
-Magnífico. how are those bets?
-José. they've got faith in you.
Don't worry. Same as always.
[man 1] Ah. Buendía!
How long you've waited to fight me.
my friend. only to be defeated?
[laughs]
-Ain't that right?
-[men laugh]
Well. I hope you have that stew cooking
'cause I'm about to kill
that rooster of yours.
[men laughing]
[crowd clamoring]
[suspenseful percussive music playing]
Woo-hoo-hoo-hoo-hoo!
-[man 1] Come on! Come on!
-[man 2] Come on!
[men shouting. clamoring]
[man 2] Yeah! Rip his head off!
[man 3] Yeah!
-[man 2] Yeah!
-[man 4] Get him! Get him!
Get him! Get him! Peck him!
Peck! Peck! Peck! Peck!
Come on! Go. rooster! Hey!
-Peck him! Kill him!
-[man 5] Go!
-Peck him!
-[all shouting]
Peck! Peck! Peck! Peck! Peck! Peck! Peck!
-[man 6] Yeah! Yeah!
-Come on!
[all clamoring]
Come on!
[men] Peck! Peck! Peck! Peck!
-[man 7] God dammit!
-[man 8] Woo-hoo-hoo!
-That's how you fucking peck!
-Come on!
That's how you fight! Rooster! Rooster!
Rooster! Rooster! Oh!
[laughs triumphantly]
Yeah!
Aw.
[man 9] What did I tell you?! [laughs]
[man 10] See? I told you!
Well. my friend… such is life.
[man 11] One. two. three!
That's a fine animal. Congratulations.
[all cheering. shouting]
-[José Arcadio B.] Careful. he's a killer.
-[man 12] Killer?
[man 13] There you go.
[man 1] Hey. Buendía!
You know. maybe that fighting cock
can finally do your wife a favor.
[man 14] Sh.
[silence]
[whispering. murmuring]
Go home and find a weapon
'cause I'm gonna kill you.
[man 15] Jesus.
-[man 16] This is bad.
-[man 17] Seriously.
[man 15] This is not good.
[tense music playing]
[man 18] Whoa! What happened?
-It was amazing.
-Right. [chuckles]
[Úrsula] José Arcadio.
José Arcadio!
[inhales. grunts]
[crowd gasping. whispering]
[man 19] He just passed.
-[sloshing]
-[groans]
[choking]
[gasps. moans] Oh!
[wheezing gasp]
If you birth iguanas.
then we'll raise iguanas.
But there'll be no more killings
in this town because of the two of us.
[solemn music playing]
[buckles jangling]
[Úrsula moaning softly]
[José and Úrsula moaning]
[moaning continues faintly]
[music fades]
[man 1] As the senior officials
of this town.
the Mayor and this humble servant
conclude that the unfortunate demise
of one Prudencio Aguilar
was. in fact. the result of
a legitimate duel of honor.
Therefore. José Arcadio Buendía.
an honorable young man.
is acquitted on all counts.
-[woman 1] No!
-[man 2] That's not justice!
-[woman 1] This is an unfair ruling!
-[man 1] Enough! Show some decorum.
[man 3] That's unjust!
[huffs]
God bless you. Thank you. sir.
My friend. the thing
that you need to do now
is to come with me
and drink your sorrows away. Hmm?
[dark barking in distance]
[eerie music playing]
What are you even doing here?
You had it coming. and you know that.
Go back to hell.
Each time you come back here.
I'm gonna kill you again.
[narrator] José Arcadio Buendía
did not dare throw his spear.
and Prudencio Aguilar did not go away.
[man chuckling]
Hand me the other one.
[narrator] They never felt
at peace after that.
-[group chatting]
-[woman laughs]
[gentle music playing]
[narrator] They were tormented
by the immense desolation
with which the dead man
had looked at them that night…
the deep nostalgia
with which he regarded the living…
[group chatting faintly]
…the anxiety with which
he searched through the house.
looking for some water
to soak the plug for his throat.
Úrsula was so moved when she saw
the dead man uncovering pots on the stove.
that she began to place water
bowls all over the house.
Why won't you just leave us alone?
[panting]
[Úrsula moaning]
You win. Prudencio.
We'll move far away from here
so you can find some peace.
and we'll never come back again.
[music fades]
Where will we go?
We'll cross the mountains
until we reach the ocean.
Don't be absurd.
No one's ever journeyed that far.
But it's possible.
What if we find somewhere new
where the fears of our ancestors
can't torment us any longer
and where you and I can
love each other freely
and raise a family?
[laughs softly]
[solemn music playing]
The ocean.
[waves crashing]
[music fades]
Thank you. Father.
Goodbye. Mother.
Úrsula…
no matter where you run.
you will never be able to
escape your true destiny.
Take care of yourself.
[sighs]
[crowd clamoring in distance]
[José Arcadio B.] All right.
off we go. my friends.
[drumbeat playing]
[mysterious music playing]
[narrator] When they left to undertake
the crossing of the mountains.
several of José Arcadio Buendía's friends.
young men like himself. followed suit.
thrilled by the adventure of it all.
They dismantled their homes.
packed up their wives and children.
and headed towards the land
that no one had promised them.
[mysterious music continues]
Water.
This is the Hanged Man…
This is that jug I promised you.
[man laughing]
-Has she read the cards to you?
-Of course. for some time now.
Thank you.
[insects chirping]
[coughs]
[gagging]
[gasping]
[pig squeals]
[snorts]
[squeals]
-[squeals]
-[screams]
[gasping]
[grunts]
[panting]
-[voices chattering]
-[birdsong]
[Úrsula groaning]
[all chatting]
[Úrsula coughing]
[wailing]
Just breathe out.
-[exhales shakily] Ooh.
-Yeah.
[wailing]
[woman] Give me a strong push!
One last push. come on!
Push! Here it comes!
Here it comes! Here it comes!
[Úrsula cries out]
[gasping]
[woman laughs. gasps]
[Úrsula whimpering]
[narrator] With her stomach ravaged by
monkey meat and snake stew.
Úrsula gave birth to a boy
with all his human body parts.
-[baby crying]
-[Úrsula crying]
[wind gusting]
[goats bleating]
[bleating]
Come on!
[all chatting]
[donkey braying]
[man 1] Whoa! Whoa! Whoa!
Whoa! Whoa! Whoa! Hey!
-Easy! Easy. boy! Easy! Easy! Easy! Easy!
-[braying loudly]
-[man 1 yelling] Oh! Oh! Oh!
-[all screaming]
[all shouting. screaming]
[man 2] Grab my hand!
[screaming continues]
Help! Help me!
[man 2] Come on. let's go! [grunting]
Come on. Geri!
[men grunting]
[all gasping]
[tense music playing]
[no audible dialogue]
Hang in there.
We'll be at the ocean in no time.
[thunder rumbling]
[rumbling fades]
[birdsong]
[narrator] After almost
two years of traveling.
they became the first mortals to witness
the western slopes of the mountain range.
[panting]
From the cloudy summit.
they saw the immense aquatic expanse
of the great swamp
stretching toward
the other side of the world.
But they never found the sea.
-You said there'd be an ocean!
-Cut it out!
-Where is it?!
-Stop!
[José Arcadio B.] Calm down. Gerineldo!
It has got to be just on the other side.
-[animals hooting]
-[insects buzzing]
[footsteps splashing]
[neighing]
[goat bleating]
Hey!
Wait! Please!
We've been moving in circles.
He has no idea where we are
or where we're going.
We have to find a way there by land.
-[all chatting]
-[birds squawking]
[narrator] One evening.
after several months of
aimlessly wandering through the swamp.
they set up camp
on the banks of a stony river
whose waters resembled
a frozen torrent of glass.
[sighs]
This great swamp must end somewhere.
We'll find a way out of this place
and then we'll
reach the ocean once and for all.
José Arcadio Buendía.
it's time for you
to finally open your eyes.
Have you stopped and looked around lately?
[travelers coughing]
[coughing continues]
[tense music playing]
[narrator] José Arcadio Buendía had
a dream that night.
He dreamt that a bustling city
rose up in that very place
full of houses with mirror walls.
He asked what the city was called.
and they answered with a name
he had never heard before.
A name that had no meaning at all.
but that echoed supernaturally
in his dream…
Macondo.
[birdsong]
[José Arcadio B.] Come on.
Come on. Come on.
Gerineldo…
I know we haven't found the sea
or a place for us to settle either…
but to keep looking for it is absurd!
Every one of you here is free
to choose your own path.
But we're going to be staying right here.
We'll build what we always envisioned.
a home for our children.
where every person can decide
how they want to live and die.
And this town of ours…
shall be called Macondo!
[triumphant percussive music playing]
[woman] How is the harvest?
[villagers chatting]
[upbeat music playing]
José Arcadio. where are your clothes?
Go home now.
[narrator] Macondo grew into
a village of 20 clay and reed houses.
They stood on the bank of a river
whose clear water ran
along a bed of polished stones.
Enormous. beautiful. white stones
like prehistoric eggs.
-[José Arcadio] Hi. Papa!
-Hey. son.
[narrator] The world was so recent.
that many things lacked names.
and the only way to refer
to them was by pointing.
[woman] José Arcadio!
Son. give this bowl of corozos
to your mommy.
Go ask her if she can
make you some juice. Hmm?
Thank you.
[narrator] José Arcadio Buendía
had arranged the houses in such a way
that each of them could access the river
and draw water with the same effort.
He laid out the streets so thoughtfully
that no one house got more sun
than another. even on the hottest of days.
[upbeat music continues]
-[José Arcadio] Hi. mama.
-Are you naked again?
Don't you have any shame?
Where did you get these corozos?
-Do you want juice?
-Mm-hmm.
All right. Come on.
Look!
It's beautiful.
-[bird chirping]
-Where will it live?
Come on!
The birdie will live here.
[music fades]
[narrator] Over the course
of the following years.
José Arcadio Buendía would fill each home
with troupials. canaries.
bee-eaters and redbreasts.
[birds chirping]
[many birds chirping]
[narrator] The daily chorus of birds
became so distressing
that Úrsula would plug
her ears with beeswax…
-Mama.
-What?
[narrator] …to keep herself from losing
all sense of reality.
Go ahead. Leave it over there.
[José Arcadio B.] Úrsula!
[Úrsula] A bed.
-Uh-huh.
-[chuckles]
Feels nice.
Well. how 'bout we try it out?
Right now?
Sh.
[Úrsula panting]
Mm.
[gasping] Uh!
[panting]
[moaning]
[distant clattering]
What was that?
[celebratory music playing]
[music builds]
[group cheering]
-[man 1] Hey! Hey!
-[man 2] Hey!
[music stops]
[crowd murmuring]
Who. exactly. are you now?
My name is Melquiades.
And this is my family.
Our fair has traveled far and wide.
And how did you find us?
The birds.
We've been crossing
the swamp for a while now
and were drawn by their singing.
It's a pleasure to meet you.
José Arcadio Buendía.
These are the people of Macondo.
-[man] Hey!
-[music resumes]
Dear friends and folks.
we've brought to these faraway lands
the eighth wonder
of the wisest alchemists of Macedonia.
If any one of you wishes
to witness firsthand
this extraordinary invention.
come with me please.
[upbeat music intensifies]
[travelers] Hey!
[music stops]
Today you shall see
how things come to life.
All you need to do is awaken their spirit.
[mysterious music playing]
[rattling]
[jangling]
[all gasp]
[music stops]
-[applause]
-[man] Bravo!
That's all witchcraft!
No. it's not.
It's just science.
If you'd like to see more.
you're invited to join us at our fair.
Music! Please. brothers!
[upbeat music playing]
[narrator] José Arcadio Buendía.
whose unbridled imagination
always went beyond
the genius of nature. miracles. and magic.
thought it might be possible
to benefit from that useless invention
and extract gold
from the bowels of the earth.
You're not trading them.
But you saw! Those things drag metal.
And these goats feed our family.
Do you realize how much gold we could get?
We don't need gold in Macondo.
My love.
Macondo won't stay like this forever.
We have to look to the future.
[goats bleating]
[upbeat mysterious music playing]
[solemn music playing]
[music stops]
[Melquiades] I'm afraid I can't sell you
the magnets for that purpose.
Your logic is sound. indeed.
But paradoxically.
they don't attract precious metals.
Well. they may not work
with smaller quantities.
but they'll surely help us unearth
all of those bigger rocks
or large heaps of treasure.
I can pay you for those.
I won't sell the magnets to you.
not for this.
There'd be nothing to gain.
Just let me try and prove it.
You'll lose nothing. Melquiades.
[laughs gently]
Very well.
I like your enthusiasm.
[birdsong]
[Magnífico] Gerineldo. what you doing?
We searched this area.
We need to look over there.
[Gerineldo] You could've
told me that before.
[Magnífico] Couldn't you tell?
You're an idiot. Just stay there.
-I'll go this way.
-[Gerineldo] Fine. fine.
[grunting]
[José Arcadio B. grunts] Hey! Over here!
[grunting. struggling]
[rumbling]
[grunts]
It has to be huge.
[all panting. grunting]
[Magnífico] A corpse.
It's been a week already.
and all we've been able
to find so far are bones and bullshit.
[both laughing]
[chuckling]
[mysterious music playing]
[music fades]
So what about all the gold
you said you would find?
You're going to
have to get our goats back.
They're no longer ours.
Well. you better go face
that lying. cheating gypsy. or I will.
We can't afford to give away
any of our animals. all right?
Especially now.
Especially now?
I'm pregnant.
[gasps. laughs]
This is great news.
[José Arcadio B.] My wife
wants nothing to do with you.
At least you saw it with your own eyes.
Experience… is everything in life.
Feel free to take your goats.
They're waiting for you.
[José Arcadio B.] Melquiades…
may I ask you something?
Of course.
How did you manage crossing
those swamps out there
without losing your way?
It was a long and difficult journey.
but we were guided the whole time
by our instruments.
What instruments?
Let me show you.
Look. This is an astrolabe.
For centuries.
humans have tried scrutinizing the skies
to help them decipher the Earth.
Here.
Science is eliminating distance.
[clattering]
Look. This is a compass.
And a sextant.
It won't be long
before man will be able to see
what is happening anywhere on Earth
without ever leaving his home.
These are Portuguese maps. Ancient.
Look.
Those tools will help you interpret them.
They're yours.
Thanks. Melquiades.
[narrator] On that day.
José Arcadio Buendía was certain
that this would be the beginning
of a great friendship.
[mysterious music playing]
He spent entire nights carefully observing
the course of the stars.
Once he became an expert
in the use and handling
of his instruments.
he understood the notion of space.
thus allowing him
to navigate unknown seas.
visit uninhabited territories.
and to establish relationships
with the most incredible beings.
[mysterious music continues]
I don't know
what you do all day with those maps.
but you have to do it somewhere else.
I want to understand where Macondo is
so we can finally find
a path to civilization.
I know the answer to that.
Macondo is here.
and you're up on the moon.
José Arcadio. it's dinnertime!
We have to wash those hands first
because they're covered in dirt. Come on.
[music fades]
Adios. Papa!
[José Arcadio B.] Goodbye. son.
-[birds squawking]
-[insects buzzing]
This galleon must be 200 years old.
It's gotta be close.
Hey! What's gotta be close?
[José Arcadio B.] The sea!
[narrator] This discovery shook
José Arcadio Buendía's spirit to its core.
He considered it a mockery of fate
to have searched for the sea
without finding it.
paying with countless sacrifices.
only to now stumble upon it
without looking at all.
We gave up on the of verge
of finding the sea. Úrsula.
Macondo is surrounded by water.
[donkey braying in distance]
[sighs]
We took several measurements.
but we still need more
in order to complete the map.
[panting]
We need to go on another expedition.
We must communicate
with the rest of world.
You can't leave us alone anymore. José.
Can't you see we need you?
[child wailing faintly]
-José Arcadio.
-[José Arcadio B.] Huh?
Listen.
[child continues wailing]
[José Arcadio B.] What is that?
[child crying]
Sh. Come here.
-[child continues crying]
-Listen.
It's crying. I hear it inside the womb.
[child continues crying]
-[woman] Matilde. the hot rags! Hurry up!
-[Matilde] I'm coming.
[Úrsula groaning] Uh!
Breathe. Just breathe. Úrsula!
That's it. Take deep breaths!
Don't push.
Don't push. don't push! Just breathe!
[narrator] Úrsula shuddered.
for she was certain
that the deep bellowing inside of her
was the first indication
of the dreaded pig tail.
[wailing]
[narrator] And she begged God
to let the creature die in her womb.
I can feel it! You can do it!
Úrsula. it's coming! It's coming!
Here it comes. Úrsula!
Come on. come on. come on!
One more push! One more! That's it!
[whimpering]
[woman] Woo-hoo!
-[Úrsula gasping] Ah! Ah! Ah!
-[woman laughing]
[Úrsula gasping] Ah! Ah! Ah! Ah! Ah!
[gasping]
[baby whimpering]
[narrator] Aureliano was
the first human being born in Macondo.
[Aureliano crying]
He was born with his eyes open.
examining the world
with an indifferent curiosity.
[Aureliano cooing]
Úrsula had forgotten
all about the intensity of that look.
until one afternoon many years later.
when Aureliano Buendía
had his first premonition.
Mama. the pot is gonna fall.
The pot's fine. Aureliano.
[mysterious music playing]
[narrator] Once he became aware
of his premonitions.
Colonel Aureliano Buendía thought one day.
his death would announce itself
with a clear.
unmistakable. and irrevocable sign.
But just moments before his death…
the sign had yet to come.
[music fades]
BASED ON THE NOVEL
BY GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ
[mysterious music playing]
[music fades]
[gentle music playing]